接下来我想为大家展示针对抗碰撞哈希函数的通用攻击
The next thing I want to do is show you
the general attack on collision resistant
如果大家还记得我们讨论分组密码时
hash functions. If you remember when we
talked about block cyphers. We saw a
我们看了一个针对分组密码的通用攻击，
我们叫它穷举攻击
general attack on block cyphers which we
called exhaustive search. And that attack
穷举攻击迫使分组密码的密钥大小是128位或更多
forced the key size for a block cypher to
be 128 bits or more. Similarly on
类似地对于抗碰撞，也有一个通用的攻击，叫做生日攻击
collision resistance there is a general
attack called the birthday attack which
也迫使抗碰撞的哈希函数的输出必须多于
forces the output of collision resistant
hash functions to be more than a certain
某个下界。我来告诉大家这个攻击，
我们会看到这些下界
bound. So let me show you the attack and
we will see what those bounds come out to
这是可以对任意抗碰撞的哈希函数使用的通用攻击
be. So here's the general attack that can
work on arbitrary collision resistant hash
这里我们有抗碰撞的哈希函数
functions. So here we have our collision
resistant hash functions, supposedly, but
假设它输出N位。换句话说，它的输出空间大小
let's suppose that it outputs N bit values.
In other words, the output space is
大约是2的N次方。现在，信息空间
roughly of size two to the N. Now, the
message space is gonna be much, much
要远远大于N位。我们说待哈希的信息
larger than N bits. Let's just say that
the messages that are being hashed are
可能有一百个N位长。我想给大家看一个算法
say, you know, a hundred times N bits. I
wanna show you an algorithm that can find
可以找到这个函数H的碰撞，用大约2的N/2次方的时间
the collision for this hash function H in
time roughly two to the N over two. Okay,
用时大约是输出空间大小的平方根
so roughly the square root of the size of
the output space. So here's how the
这个算法如下工作：我们从信息空间里随机选择
algorithms gonna work: what we'll do is
we'll choose random two to the N over two
2的N/2次方个信息，即M1,M2...M_2^N/2
messages in our message space that's
called an M-one to M-two to the N over
现在因为信息本身远远大于N位
two. Now because the messages themselves
are much bigger than N bits, they're
它们有上百个N位，很有可能这些信息是不相同的
hundred times N bits, it's very likely
that all these messages are distinct. So
它们互不相同的概率很大。但对每一条选中的信息
they'll be distinct with high probability.
But for each one of these messages we're
我们应用哈希函数，获得标签T_i
gonna apply the hash function and obtain
the tag T sub I. So this is of course the
当然这个T_i是N位字符串。现在我们在T_i中
T sub I's are N-bit long strings. And now
we're gonna look for a collision among the
寻找一个碰撞。换句话说，我们找一个i和j
T sub I's. In other words, we're gonna
find an I and a J such that T sub I equals
满足T_i=T_j，一旦我们找到了，就等于是发现了碰撞
to T sub J. And once we've done that we've
basically found the collision because, as
因为如前所述，以很高的概率，M_i不等于M_j
we said, with very high probability, M-I
is not equal to M-J. But the hash of M-I
但M_i的哈希值等于M_j的哈希值。因此，
我们找到了函数H的碰撞
is equal to the hash of M-J and therefore
we found the collision on the function H.
现在如果我们找遍了这2的N/2次方个T_i
Now if it so happens that we looked
through all the two to the N over two T
却没有找到碰撞，我们回到第一步
sub I's and we don't find the collision,
we go back to step one and try another set
尝试另一组2的N/2次方个信息。问题是，这个攻击效果如何？
of two to the N over two messages. So the
question is how well will this work, in
换句话说，我们需要迭代这个过程多少次
other words how many times do we have to
iterate this process until we actually
直到发现碰撞？我想告诉大家事实上
find the collision? And I wanna show you
that in fact the number of iterations is
迭代次数是个非常小的数，意味着这个算法可以找到碰撞
gonna be very, very small which means that
this algorithm will find the collision in
以大约正比于2的N/2次方的时间。为了分析这种攻击
time that's roughly proportional two to
the N over two. So to analyze this type of
我必须告诉大家一点关于生日悖论的知识
attack, I have to tell you a little bit
about the birthday paradox. I imagine some
我想一些人已经听说过生日悖论了
of you have already heard about the
birthday paradox. Here stated as a
这里写成定理的形式，我想给大家证明之，
因为每个人都应该一辈子至少见过一次
theorem, and I wanna prove it to you
because everybody should see a proof of
生日悖论的证明。那么这就是证明
the birthday paradox at least once in
their lives. So here it is, so imagine we
设想我们有N个随机变量R1,R2,...,R_N，取值范围
在从1到B的区间里
have N random variables R-one to R-N in
the interval one to B. And the only thing
我的唯一的假设是，这N个随机变量是相互独立的
I'm gonna assume about them is that
they're actually independent of one
这N个样本R1,...,R_N在这个区间里相互独立是很重要的
another. That's crucial that these N
samples R-one to R-N in this interval are
而且它们还是同分布的
independent of one another. And they also
happen to be distributed identically. So
例如，它们可能都是在从1到B的区间里均匀分布的
for example, they might all be uniform in
the interval one to B, but again these
但它们还是独立的均匀分布的变量。但如果我们
would be independently uniform variables.
Now it so happens that if we set N to B
把N设置为B的平方根大小，换句话说，如果我们
从区间1到B内取样约B的平方根次
about the square root of B, in other words
if we sample roughly the square root of B
精确地说，是1.2乘以B的平方根次
samples from the interval one to B, And to
be precise, it's one point two times the
那么样本中有两个是一样的概率
square root of B. Then the probability
that two of those samples will be the same
至少是1/2。事实上均匀分布
is at least a half. Okay, then it turns
out in fact the uniform distribution is
是生日悖论中的最坏情况。换句话说
the worst case for the birthday paradox.
In other words, if the distribution from
如果Ri取样的分布不是均匀的，事实上
which the R-I's are sampled from is
non-uniform, that in fact fewer than one
需要的取样次数要少于1.2乘以B的平方根
point two times the square root of B
samples are needed. The uniform
均匀分布是最坏的情况。那么我们证明均匀分布的情况
distribution is the worst case. So we're
gonna prove this for the uniform
也就能证明其他分布的情况
distribution and that basically also
proves it for all other distributions. But
但我们这里给大家的证明只对均匀分布成立
the proof that I wanna show you here will
hold just for the uniform distribution.
我们来进行这个并不困难的证明
Okay, so let's do the proof that's
actually not difficult at all. So we're
我们要求，存在一对i和j，i不等于j
asking what is the probability that there
exists an I that is not equal to J such
满足Ri等于Rj的概率。我们求互斥事件的概率，
就是说我们所求概率为1减去
that RI is equal to RJ. Well, let's negate
that so it's basically one minus the
对所有i不等于j都有Ri不等于Rj的概率
probability that for all I not equal to J
we have that RI is not equal to RJ. This
这意味着我们选择的N个样本里没有发生碰撞
basically means that no collision occurred
among the N samples that we chose. Well
我们试着更精确地把这个写下来
let's try to write this out more
precisely. Well we're gonna write this as
我们写成1减去某个数的形式。现在当我们选择
R1时，这是我们第一次选择
one minus. And now when we choose R-one,
basically it's the first one we choose so
所以是不会发生任何碰撞的。但现在当我们取R2时
it's not gonna collide with anything. But
now let's look at what happens when we
我问大家，R2不与R1碰撞的概率是多少？
choose R-two, when we choose R-two, let me
ask you, what is the probability that
R1已经占了一个位置，所以有B-1个剩余位置
R-two does not collide with R-one? Well,
R-one takes one slot so there are B minus
如果R2落在这B-1个剩余位置中，将不会与R1碰撞
one slots that if R-two falls into it's
not gonna collide with R-one. So in other
换句话说，R2不与R1碰撞的概率是
words the probability that R-two does not
collide with R-one is B minus one slot
(B-1)/B。类似地，当我们选择R3时
divided by all B possible slots.
Similarly, when we pick R-three, what is
R3不与R1或R2碰撞的概率是多少？
the probability that R-three does not
collide with either R-one or R-two? Again,
同样的，R1和R2占了两个位置，所以有B-2个剩余位置
R-one and R-two take up two slots. And so
there are B minus two slots that remain
如果R3落在B-2个剩余位置中的任何一个
for R-three if it falls into either one of
those B minus two slots it's not gonna
将不会与R1或R2发生碰撞。我想大家已看出这个模式了
collide with either R-one or R-two. So I
imagine you see the pattern now, so R-four
R4不与R1,R2,R3碰撞的概率是(B-3)/B
it's probability of not colliding with
R-one, R-two, or R-three is B minus three
等等。。直到我们获得了最后的R_N
over B. And so on and so forth until we
get to the very last R-N and the
R_N不与之前所有Ri碰撞的概率是多少？
probability that R-N does not collide with
the previous R-I's, well, there are N
有N-1个位置已经被前面的Ri占了。
如果R_N落在了剩下的B-N+1个位置中
minus one slots taken up by the previous
R-I's. So, if R-N falls into any of the
它将不会和任何前面的R1到R_N-1发生碰撞
remaining B minus N plus one slots, it's
not gonna collide with any of the previous
现在大家注意到，我可以把这些概率乘起来的原因
R-one to R-N minus one. Now you notice
that the reason I was able to multiply all
正是因为这些Ri是相互独立的
these probabilities is exactly because the
R-I's are all independent of one another.
对于这步来说独立性很重要。这些Ri是相互独立的
So it's crucial for the step. That the
R-I's are independent. So let me rewrite
让我把这个表达式稍微重写一下。我把它写成
1减去i从1到N-1，1-i/B的乘积
this expression a little bit. Let me write
it as one minus the product of I goes to N
我只是把它写成了一个大乘积的形式
minus one of one minus I over B. Okay. All
I did is I just rewrote this as a big
而不是逐项写出。现在我将使用
product as opposed to writing the terms
individually. So now I'm gonna use the
标准不等式，告诉我们对任何正X
standard inequality that says that for any
positive X, one minus X is less than E to
1-X小于e^-X。这是容易看出的，因为e^-X
the minus X. And that's actually easy to
see because E to the minus X, if you look
如果你看它的泰勒展开，是1减去X加上X的平方
除以2，再减去。。等等
at its Taylor expansion, is one minus X
plus X squared over two minus and so on
你可以看到我们忽略了泰勒展开的高次项
and so forth. And so you can see that
we're basically ignoring this latter part
高次项正好是正的，因此
of the Taylor expansion, which happens to
be positive and as a result the left side
左边比右边小。我们带入这个不等式
is gonna be smaller than the right-hand
side. Okay, so let's plug this inequality
得到什么呢？我们得到这个概率大于1减去
in, and what do we get? We get that this
is greater than one minus the product of I
i从1到N-1，e^-i/B的乘积
goes from one to N minus one of E to the
minus I over B okay, simply plugged in X
各项带入X=i/B即可。接下来
equals I over B for each one of those
terms. And the next thing about
指数值相乘只需将指数相加。因此
exponentials is that we multiply them, the
exponents add. As a result this is simply
这是1减去e的某个次方，这里我把1/B
equal to one minus E to the power of, here
let me take the one over B out of the
从括号里提取了出来，指数变成了i从1到N-1，各项之和
parentheses, sum of I goes from one to N
minus one of I. Okay. So, all I did was I
我把-1/B从括号里提取出来，只剩下
took the minus one over B out of the
parentheses and we're left with simple sum
从1到N-1的简单求和了。1到N-1的整数和
of one to N minus one. And so the sum of
the integers from 1 to N minus one is
是N乘以N-1除以2，有上界N平方除以2
simply N times N minus one over two which
it can bound by N squared over two. And so
所以我这里最终得到的是1减去e^(-N^2/B)
really what I get at the end here is one
minus E to the power of minus N squared
好，我这里用N平方除以2来表示这个求和
over two B. Okay, I literally downed it to
sum here by N squared over two. Okay, very
很好。那么现在对于N平方除以2B，我们能做什么？
good. So now what do we do about N squared
over two B? Well, we can derive exactly
我们可以从这里的关系精确地推出N平方除以2B是什么
what N squared over two B is from the
relationship here. So if you think about
如果考虑N平方除以2是1.2的平方除以2
it, let's look at N squared over two.
Well, N squared over two is 1.2 squared
1.2的平方是1.44，除以2是0.72
over two. 1.2 squared is 1.44 divided by
two is .72 times the square root of B
0.72乘以B的平方根的平方，也就是B。好
N平方除以2是0.72B，因此
squared which is B. Okay so N squared over
two is .72B, and as a result, N squared
N平方除以2B就是0.72。这样我们获得了1-e^-0.72
over 2B is just .72. So we get 1-E, which
is a power of minus 0.72. Well so now you
现在使用计算器，可以算出答案是0.53
just plug this in to your calculator and
you get 0.53, which as far as I know, is
目前我知道，0.53总是大于F的。这就证明了生日悖论
always bigger than F. So this proves the
Birthday Paradox and you notice that it
大家注意到样本的相互独立性的重要性了
was crucial to a string that the samples
are independent of one another, we only
我们只证明了均匀分布的情况。不过我说过
proved that for the uniform distribution.
But as I said it is actually fairly easy
实际上容易证明，任何不是均匀分布的分布
to argue now that any distribution that is
away from the uniform distribution will
都会以一个更低的下界满足该性质。如果你有
1.2乘以B的平方根个样本
satisfy this with even a lower balance. So
if you have 1.2 squared of B, the theorem
这个定理对非均匀分布也当然成立
will certainly hold for non-uniform
distributions. The reason it is called a
它之所以被称为悖论，是因为平方根函数增长缓慢
paradox is because it is very paradoxical
that the square root function grows very
与人的直觉相悖。特别地，如果你试图把这个
应用到生日上
slowly. In particular if you try to apply
this to birth dates, so let's assume that
我们假设一间房间里有很多人，假设他们的生日
we have a number of people in a room, and
let's assume that their birth dates are
互相独立，而且是365天均匀分布的
independent of one another and are uniform
in their interval one through 365. Then
那么生日悖论告诉我们，我们需要约1.2乘以365的平方根
what the Birthday Paradox says is that we
need roughly 1.2 times the square root of
我想也就是约23人，在一个房间里
365. Which i believe is something like 23,
which says we need roughly 23 people in a
以概率1/2，其中有两人有着相同的生日
room, and then with probability one half,
two of them will actually have the same
它被称为悖论的原因，是因为对人来说
birth date. The reason it is called a
paradox is because the number 23 seems
23似乎是很小的，根据这个定理，我们证明了
really small to people, and yet by this
theorem we just proved, with probability
以1/2的概率，23人中会有两人的生日相同
one half, there will be two people with
the same birth date. By the way the
顺便一说，这个事实成立的直观解释是：
因为碰撞实际上
intuition for why this fact is true is
because really what the collision is
是要看所有可能的配对。如果你有
counting is it is looking at all possible
pairs of people. And if you have a square
B的平方根个人，那么就有了B^2的平方根个配对
root of B people, then there are square
root of B squared pairs. Roughly, which is
大约就是B个配对，因此很有可能每个配对
roughly B pairs total and so it's very
likely that each pair collides probability
以1/B的概率碰撞，如果你有B个配对，就很有可能
其中有一个配对发生了碰撞
one over B and if you have B pairs, it's
likely that one of the pairs will collide.
希望这能给出这个平方根的直观解释
So hopefully this gives the intuition for
where the square root comes from. It's
这是基于一个事实，如果房间里有N个人
basically from the fact that if you have N
people in the room, there are N squared
就有N平方个可能的配对。我应该顺便一说，
即使生日悖论经常被用到生日上
possible pairs. I should say by the way
that even though the Birthday Paradox is
生日实际上却根本不是均匀分布的
often applied to birth dates, birth dates
are actually not uniform at all. If you
如果你看实际中人们的生日，可以看到
actually look at the birth dates of
people, you see that there is a very clear
九月的生日有明显的不均匀，而且出于某些奇葩原因
bias towards being born in September, and
for me bazaar reason there is also a
星期二出生的也有不均匀。所以当我们对生日
biased towards being born on a Tuesday.
And so when we apply the birthday paradox
应用生日悖论时，事实上下界还要比
1.2乘以B的平方根更低些
to birthdays, in fact the actual bound is
going to be smaller than one point two
因为我们说过，对于不均匀的分布来说
square root of B because we said that for
non even form distributions you need even
在碰撞前，你需要更少的样本。我给大家看
fewer samples before you get a collision.
So let me show you how to graph the
生日悖论的图表。它的表现很有趣
Birthday Paradox, its quite interesting
how it behaves. So here set B to be a
这里B设置为一百万，换句话说，我们从1到一百万中
均匀随机地选取样本
million, in other words we are picking
random uniform samples in the range one to
这里X轴是我们选取的样本数
a million. And the X axis here, is the
number of samples that we are picking, and
Y轴是我们选取的样本中发生碰撞的概率
the Y axis, is the probability that we get
a collision among those N samples. So we
我们看到，1/2概率发生在1.2乘以B的平方根附近
see that the probability of one half
happens around 1.2 square root of B.
约1200，即1.2倍的B的平方根。大家看到
Roughly twelve hundreds, 1.2 square root
of B. And you see that if we look at
如果我们就看B的平方根，碰撞概率约0.4
exactly the square root of B, the
probability of a collisions is around .4
或0.41.大家注意到这个概率很快地逼近1
or .41. And you notice that the
probability goes up to one extremely fast.
例如，在大约2倍的B的平方根处
For example, already at roughly two square
root of B, but the probability of a
碰撞概率已经达到90%。类似的，当我们看
低于B的平方根的部分时
collision is already 90%. Similarly, when
we go bellow square root of B, the
碰撞概率以非常快的速度减到0
probability of a collision very, very
quickly drops to zero. Okay, so there is
在B的平方根处，有一个阈值效应
kind of a threshold phenomena around
square root of B, where the probability of
在B的平方根之上，碰撞概率很快逼近1；
在B的平方根之下，碰撞概率很快逼近0
a collision goes to one very quickly,
above square root of B drops to zero very
现在我们可以分析攻击算法了
quickly below square root of B. So now we
can analyze the attack algorithms, so let
我提醒一下大家，这里我们选择区间中的两个数
me remind you, here we chose, two to the
interval two random elements in the
信息空间中的两个随机元素，我们求它们的哈希值。
我们从这个信息空间的一个随机分布开始
message space, we hashed them. And so we
started off with a random distribution in
在我们求它们的哈希值后，我们最终得到了某个分布
the message space, after we hashed them, we
end up with some distribution, this
这个标签上的分布可能不是均匀的，我们不在乎
distribution over tags might not be
uniform, but we don't care, the point is
关键是所有这些标签T1,T2,...,T_N/2，是互相独立的
that all these tags T1 to T2 to the N over
two, are independent of one another. If we
如果我们选择2的N/2次方或1.2的N/2次方个标签
choose two to the N over two or 1.2 to
the N over two, tags, the probability that
存在碰撞的概率大约是1/2。那么我问大家
the collision will exist is roughly one
half. So let me ask you then, in that
这时，我们必须迭代这个算法多少次
case, how many times do we have to iterate
this algorithm before we actually find a
直到发现一个碰撞呢？由于每轮迭代会以1/2的概率
collision? Well then since each iteration
is going to find a collision with
找到碰撞，我们平均需要迭代两次
probability one half, we have to iterate
about two times in expectation. And as a
因此这个算法的运行时间是2的N/2次方
result the running time of this algorithm
is basically two to the N over two
乘以哈希函数的计算时间。也要注意，这个算法
evaluations of the hash function. Okay so
notice also this algorithm takes a lot of
需要大量的空间，但我们先忽略空间的问题
space but we're gonna ignore the space
issue and we're just gonna focus on the
仅关注运行时间。这个方法很不错
running time. Okay so this is kinda cool,
this says that if your hash
如果你的哈希函数输出N位，总是存在一个攻击算法
function outputs N-bits outputs
there will always be an attack algorithm
用2的N/2次方的时间发现碰撞。比如，如果我们输出128位
that runs in time two to the N over two.
So for example if we output 128 bit
在2的64次方的时间里，可以找到一个碰撞
outputs. Then a collision could be found in
time two to the sixty four, which is not considered
这将不是充分安全的。好，这就是为什么抗碰撞的哈希函数
sufficiently secure. Okay, this is why
collision resistant hash functions,
通常不输出128位。我给大家看一些例子
generally are not going to output 128
bits. So let me show you some examples.
第一批三个联邦标准：SHA-1，SHA-256和SHA-512
The first three are actually federal
standards, SHA-1, SHA-256, and SHA-512
第四个是来自AES的设计者们的，叫做Whirlpool
and the fourth one is an example from
the designers of AES, called Whirlpool,
你能看到SHA-1输出160位，因此一个通用攻击
and so you can see SHA-1 outputs 160
bits and as a result there is a generic
运行时间为2的80次方，SHA-256输出256位
attack on it that runs on
time two to the eighty. SHA-256 outputs 256
通用攻击运行时间为2的128次方，等等
bits so the generic attack will run
in time two to the 128 and so on and so
我也把这些算法的速度列在这里了。大家注意到
forth. I also listed the speed of these
algorithms and you notice that the bigger
分组越大，算法越慢
the block size actually the slower the
algorithm is. So there's a
有一个性能上的亏损，但安全性上有很多好处
performance penalty but nevertheless
there's quite a bit of benefit in terms of
大家注意SHA函数是灰色的
security. Now you notice the SHA
function is actually greyed out. The
尽管没有人发现SHA-1的碰撞
SHA function although nobody has
found collisions for SHA-1 yet
在新项目里，编程项目里
It is still recommended that in a new
project, and hopefully programing projects
不推荐使用SHA-1。可以使用SHA-256
in this class, you don't use SHA-1,
instead you use SHA-256. In particular
特别地，SHA-1有一个理论上的碰撞发现算法
there is actually a theoretical collision
finder on SHA-1 that works in time two
(2的51次方的攻击被原作者收回了，目前最好的是2^61)
需要2的51次方的时间。所以某人发现一个
SHA-1的碰撞几乎只是时间问题
to the 51. So it is probably just a matter
of time until someone finds a collision
所以这些都不能用了。目前的建议是
for SHA-1, and just kills altogether,
but the current advice is that SHA-1 is
SHA-1依然算一个抗碰撞的哈希函数，
因为还没有人能找到碰撞
still a collision resistant hash function
because nobody has found collisions for
但是几乎只是时间问题，可能几个月，或几年
it, but it is probably just a matter of
time, just a few months, or few years,
直到一个碰撞被发现。这个结果告诉我们，
新的产品和项目不应再用SHA-1
until a collision is found. It is a result
a new product and new projects SHA-1
应该只用SHA-256
should not be used and only use
SHA-256 or if you wanna be even
如果你想更谨慎点，可以使用SHA-512
more cautious then use SHA-512. So this is the end of this
本节完结，现在我们看如何构建抗碰撞的哈希
segment, and now we are going to turn
building collision resistant hash